Finding Aid for Gary M. Olson papers, 1986-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gary M. Olson papers 1986-1989
Olson, Gary M.
3 linear feet
0672 Aa 2
The Gary M. Olson papers largely document the work done at the University of Michigan and Carnegie Mellon University, during the mid-1980s, to create a computer application called the Experimental Research in Electronic Submission (EXPRES). The goal of the work was to create a collaborative, networked application, which would allow researchers - using different hardware and software environments - to electronically share research. The EXPRES application was intended for electronic submission of grant proposals to the National Science Foundation (NSF).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from Gary Olson (Donor no. 9679 ) in a single accession in 2005.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gary M. Olson is a professor of Human Computer Interaction (HCI) at the University of Michigan School of Information and also serves as a professor in the Department of Psychology. From 1984 to 1995, Olson served at the director of the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL), a joint venture of the School of Business Administration, the College of Engineering, and the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Olson also served as the interim dean at the School of Information from 1998 to 1999. Olson's research interest is in applied cognitive science, with a focus on human-computer interaction and computer-supported cooperative work. During the mid 1980s, he participated on the EXPRES project to help improve the communication between researchers across the country.
The Experimental Research in Electronic Submission (EXPRES) project was led at Michigan by Daniel E. Atkins. Atkins served as the dean at the School of Information and an associate dean at the College of Engineering. His work at the university encompassed many projects that looked to make scientific research a more collaborative process.
The National Science Foundation (NSF) provided funding for the EXPRES project, hoping to use the application as a way to submit and review grant proposals electronically. In June 1986, NSF asked for proposals to create the EXPRES application, which were awarded to the Carnegie Mellon University and the University of Michigan.
Another goal of the EXPRES project, beyond electronic submission, was to help researchers collaborate in an electronic environment. Before the creation of electronic communication standards and software applications of this nature, it was difficult to electronically share research with colleagues because of the limitations in the hardware, software, and network environments and the differences among universities and their computer mainframe systems. Through the use of the EXPRES software application, improvements in micro and mainframe computing, and improvements in communication via the Internet, knowledge sharing in an electronic format became an easier process.
In several ways, the EXPRES application was ahead of its time. While it did not fully succeed, it identified many of the issues which were overcome with new technologies. According to Science magazine and NSF, for a couple of years the project managed a "few hundred proposals ... before NSF officials realized that they had bitten off more than they could chew".[1] EXPRES's challenges included "hard-to-use software, balky transmission lines, and incompatibility with existing systems."[2] The average computer user at the time was not able to use EXPRES. In the mid 1990s, NSF tried a different application called FastLane, which though smaller, was a more manageable system for researchers to use. FastLane, as of 2008, is still being used by NSF for submission and review of proposals.
_____________________________
Notes:
1) Jeffery Mervis, "NSF Moves Into FastLane to Manage Flow of Grants," Science 267 (1995): 166-167.
2) Ibid.
The Gary M. Olson papers largely document the work done at the University of Michigan and Carnegie Mellon University, during the mid-1980s, to create a computer application called the Experimental Research in Electronic Submission (EXPRES). The papers do not fully document Olson's career. Rather they give insight a key collaborative project. The papers have been organized into four series: Meetings and Reports; Publicity and Presentations; Publications; and Subject Files.
Subjects:
Human-computer interaction.; Information technology.; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Olson, Gary M.; University of Michigan. Experimental Research in Electronic Submission Project.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Meetings and Reports 1986-1988
  The Meetings and Reports (1 linear ft.) series, spanning 1986-1988, has been sorted chronologically. It contains the project proposal to the NSF. It also contains several files about various site visits taken to Carnegie Mellon, Cambridge, and the NSF. Electronic mail (printed out) correspondence is in this series. Also in this series are technical reviews, project plans, and meeting minutes of the development team.
  - Technical Review of the Effort to Port Diamond and Cronus to the HP9020A Workstation: Final Report December 1986 (Box 1)
  - Proposal to the National Science Foundation for a Cooperative Agreement for Experimental Research in Electronic Submission (EXPRES) of Multimedia Proposals and Documents August 1986 (Box 1)
  - NSF EXPRES Site Visit September 10, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Cambridge Visit December 11-12, 1986 (Box 1)
  - EXPRES Meeting, BBN Laboratories December 12, 1986 (Box 1)
  - NSF Trip January 7-8, 1987 (Box 1)
  - NSF, Carnegie Mellon University (CMU) Trip January 27-28, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Meeting at NSF February 12, 1987 (Box 1)
  - BBN Visit to UM March 4-6, 1987 (Box 1)
  - National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Visit March 27, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Project Management Committee (PMC) Meeting July 22, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Needs, Requirements, and Evaluation Group (NRE) Report August 7, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Technical Review September 10-11, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Engineering National Advisory Committee (NAC) October 1987 (Box 1)
  - Areas of work for UM EXPRES Development Team October 1987 (Box 1)
  - UM EXPRES Development Team Progress Report November 4, 1987 (Box 1)
  - UM EXPRES Project Review and Plans for Year 2 December 13, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Project Management Committee (PMC) Meeting December 16, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Postscript Experiment, Interim Report April 4, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Interoperability Meeting April 7, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee April 7-8, 1988 (Box 1)
  - UM EXPRES Goals and Mid-Course Plan June 22, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Project Management Committee (PMC) Meeting September 2, 1988 (Box 1)
  - CMU-EXPRES Progress Report October 1987-September 1988 (Box 1)
  - Net Express Meeting at Ann Arbor November 14-15, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Technical Advisory Committee Meeting November 14-15, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Technical Advisory Panel November 1988 (Box 1)
  - UM EXPRES Project Review and Plans for Year 3 November 30, 1988 (Box 1)
- Publicity and Presentations 1987-1989
  The Publicity and Presentations series (.5 linear ft.), covering 1987-1989, has been sorted chronologically. The series contains newsletters about the EXPRES software application. It contains presentations given at various conferences of the software application. There is electronic mail (printed out) correspondence in this series. The series also contains the draft of a chapter, "Supporting Collaboration with Advanced Multimedia Electronic Mail: The NSF EXPRES Project," that Gary Olson and Daniel Atkins co-wrote for a book titled Intellectual Teamwork: Social and Technological Foundations of Cooperative Work.
  - Presentation Materials (Box 2)
  - Demos at Conferences, Hanover Fair (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Highlighted at Ann Arbor Meeting (Box 2)
  - EXPRES -- Seminar Series November 1986-January 1987 (Box 2)
  - Langenberg Panel (Information Technologies and the Conduct of Research) January 8, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) Bulletin, Issue 19 "EXPRES Project," January 12, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Andrew Demo April 14, 1987 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Newsletter, Vol. 1, no. 1 June 1987 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) Event June 8, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Trip Report: Technical Support for Work Group Collaboration (NYU Symposium) June 28, 1987 (Box 2)
  - EDUCOM (Los Angeles) 1987 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Initiative Unix in the Office, Vol. 10, no. 11 November 1987 (Box 2)
  - Combined Trip Report: ANSI X3V1 Meeting, NBS OSI Implementers Workshop November 2, 1987 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Videotape Notes and Correspondence November-December 1987 (Box 2)
  - Chapter on EXPRES, Kraut et al Book 1988 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Newsletter, Vol. 2, no. 1, January 1988 (Box 2)
  - CSNET News: "EXPRES Project Completes First Year" No. 16 1988 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES Event March 4-5, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Baseline Studies of Current Practice: Methods and Some Significant Results (Transparencies) March 1988 (Box 2)
  - Article: "Computer Giants Back UM EXPRES" University Record, Special Report "Getting the Job Done," April 18, 1988 (Box 2)
  - The Carnegie-Mellon University (CMU) Open Document Architecture Consortium February 28, 1989 (Box 2)
- Publications 1987-1988
  The Publications series (.5 linear ft.), 1987-1988, has been sorted chronologically. It contains user manuals for different versions of EXPRES as well as one on Diamond Multimedia Document System.
  - Installing and Using MMDeliver on the Sun 3, Sun 4, and Sun 386i (Box 2)
  - Sending Mail with Diamond Release 4.1 on the Sun 3, Sun 4, and Sun 386i (Box 2)
  - UM EXPRES Tutorial (Box 2)
  - Diamond Multimedia Document System: Tutorial, Release 3 February 1987 (Box 2)
  - Diamond User's Reference Guide, Release 3.1 November 1987 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES User's Reference Guide, UM EXPRES 1.0 January 1988 (Box 2)
  - Diamond Multimedia Document System, User's Reference Guide, Release 3.2 June 1988 (Box 2)
  - EXPRES User's Reference Guide, UM EXPRES 2.0 July 1988 (Box 2)
  - UM EXPRES 2.0 Release August 31, 1988 (Box 2)
- Subject Files 1986-1989
  The Subject Files series (1 linear ft.), covers, 1986-1989, and has been sorted alphabetically. The deployment of the EXPRES software application is documented in this series. Other topics include the Diamond software, files on the current (1988) state of EXPRES, and NSF files.
  - Carnegie Mellon University (CMU) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Misc. (Box 3)
  - Deployment 1987 (Box 3)
  - Deployment: Beta Test Agreements (Box 3)
  - Deployment: Data Capture (Box 3)
  - Deployment: Sites (Box 3)
  - Diamond (Box 3)
  - Diamond 3.1 (Box 3)
  - Diamond Dialogue Boxes (Box 3)
  - EXPRES (Box 3)
  - EXPRES -- Current (Box 3)
  - EXPRES Directory Listing (Box 3)
  - EXPRES -- Now (Box 3)
  - EXPRES -- Project (Box 3)
  - Legal Materials (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) (Box 3)
  - NSF -- Astronomy (Box 3)
  - NSF -- Atmospheric Sciences (Box 3)
  - NSF -- CISE (Box 3)
  - Other Universities (Box 3)
  - Other Universities (Box 3)
  - Project Management Notes (Box 3)
  - Research Plans (Box 3)
  - Site Selection (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Atmospheric Sciences (Box 3)
  - User Trials Task Force (Box 3)
Related Material
For additional material on EXPRES, researchers are encouraged to consult these additional holdings at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan. College of Engineering records (Associate Dean, Dan Atkins files)
University of Michigan. Information Technology Division records
University of Michigan. Computing Center records
For further information on Gary Olson and the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) he directed from 1984 to 1985, researchers should consult the following records:
University of Michigan. Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory.